Guide to the Italian Castle Archive
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- HISTORICAL DOCUMENTS, 59 manuscript documents on 772 pages, numbered ff.
  - (Odoardo Farnese, Duke of Parma and Pope Urban VIII). A letter concerning hostilities between the Duke of Parma and Pope Urban VIII in the matter of Castro, with references to the Duke's published Relazione on the subject. Undated and unsigned (c. 1642). This letter was published in the first volume (p. 791) of Vittorio Siri's Mercurio. 27 pages, numbered ff. 228-241. (Box 94, Folder 37)
  - Trovandosi il Principe Matthias (de'Medici) nello Stato di Siena... A report concerning the Duke of Parma's fight for Castro. Undated, unsigned. (c. 1642). 26 pages, numbered ff. 243-255. (Box 94, Folder 38)
  - (Spada, Giovanni Battista, Governor of Rome). Al Marchese de los Veles. Copy of a letter by Spada to the Spanish Ambassador concerning the Duke of Parma and Castro. Undated, unsigned. 3 pages, numbered ff. 256-257. (Box 94, Folder 39)
  - Relatione della Valorosa difesa della Pietose Citta di Pistoia dalla furiosa soppresa dell'Armi Barbarine. An account of the defense of Pistoia, another chapter in the War of the Barberini. Undated, unsigned (c. 1640). 8 pages, numbered ff. 258-261. (Box 94, Folder 40)
  - Raccolta di tutte le concessioni, donationi, et investiture fatte del Ducato d'Urbino in cominciando da Pipino Re di Francia sino al tempi di Pio IV. An account of the donations, concessions, and investitures by the Dukedom of Urbino from the 8th to the 16th centuries. The Brit. Mus. Catalogue lists Memorie istoriche concernenti la devoluzione dello stato di Urbino alla sede Apostolica, Amsterdam, 1723, which might be the published version of this manuscript. 14 pages, numbered ff. 263-269. (Box 94, Folder 41)
  - Louis XIV, King of France. Copy of a letter by Louis XIV to Cardinal Francesco Barberino, signed and dated Paris, Dec. 22, 1645. 2 pages (f. 271). (Box 94, Folder 42)
  - Barberini, Cardinal Francesco. Replica. Copy of Barberino's answer to Louis XIV, dated Rome, Jan. 10, 1646. 4-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 272-274. (Box 94, Folder 43)
  - Barberini, Cardinal Francesco. Lettera lasciata al Sacro Collegio... Copy of Barberini's letter to the Sacred College, left there before fleeing from Rome to France on Jan. 16, 1646, and the Cardinals' answer, dated Jan. 25, 1646. 15 pages, numbered ff. 274-281. (Box 94, Folder 44)
  - Ragguaglio Di quanto e seguito intorno alla Comprotettione di Francia data al Sig. Card. Antonio Barberino in Sin alli 29 d'Aprile 1634. A report of the protection France gave to the Cardinal Barberini, one of the diplomatic steps in France's increasing hostility towards Rome. Copy, unsigned, dated April 29, 1634. 29 pages, numbered ff. 282-295. (Box 94, Folder 45)
  - Relatione della fuga SS.ri. Duca e Duchessa di Lorena dal Castello di Nansi ove erano Custoditi dalle Forze Francesci. An account of the flight from Nancy of Charles IV, Duke of Lorraine, in 1634. Undated, unsigned. 24 pages, numbered ff. 296-307. (Box 94, Folder 46)
  - Relatione dello stato e forze di tutti i Principi d'Italia. A detailed report on the Italian states, their princes, assets, etc. Undated, unsigned. Probably at the beginning of the 17th century. 30 pages, numbered ff. 308-322. (Box 94, Folder 47)
  - (Ferdinand II, Emperor). Sponte restituta stratagemate captum... Latin panegyric for Ferdinand II after his victories in the 30 Years' War. 8 pages, numbered ff. 324-327. Undated and unsigned, c. 1635. (Box 94, Folder 48)
  - (Ferdinand II, Emperor). Sommario delli Articoli della Pace tra l'Imperatore et l'Elettore di Sassonia trattata a Pirna e publicata à Praga l'anno 1635. Summary of the negotiations for a separate peace between Emperor Ferdinand II and the Elector John George of Saxony, 1635. 17 pages, numbered ff. 328-336. (Box 94, Folder 49)
  - (Estampes-Valencay, Henri d'). Relatione della Corte di Roma del Bali di Valencia al novo Ambascitor di Francia. A report by Valençay, French Ambassador in Rome, to his successor. Undated, unsigned (c. 1653). 36 pages, numbered ff. 337-354. (Box 94, Folder 50)
  - Ragionamento fatto nel Senato Veneto dall'Ambasciadore di Spagna residente in Venetia sopra li correnti affari di guerra. Tensions between the Spanish Ambassador and the Senate of Venice. Undated and unsigned. 9 pages, numbered ff. 355-359. (Box 94, Folder 51)
  - Pesaro, Giovanni. Dalla relatione...fatta in Venetia tornato dall'Ambasciatura... Report by Pesaro on his embassy in Rome, 1656. 2 pages (f. 361). (Box 94, Folder 52)
  - Alexander VII, Pope. Dilectiis Filiis Nob. Viris, Bertuccio Valerio Duci et Reipub. Venetiae. Copies of 2 letters of the Pope to Venice concerning the reinstatement of the Jesuits in Venice. Dated 23 Feb., 1656 and 27 Jan., 1657. 4 pages, numbered ff. 362-363. (Box 94, Folder 53)
  - Copia della resposta della Republica di Venetia alla Santita Alessandro VII. Copy of the answer to the Pope's letter (see preceding number). Undated, unsigned. (1656 or 1657). 1 page (f. 364). (Box 94, Folder 54)
  - Copie di Lettere scritte dale P. Generale alla Republica...di Venetia. Copies of 2 letters written by the Jesuit General to Venice regarding the reinstatement of the Jesuits there. Unsigned, undated (c. 1657). 2 pages (f. 365). (Box 94, Folder 55)
  - (Republic of Venice). Copies of three letters: to the French Ambassador Du Plessis, to Louis XIV, and to Cardinal Mazarin, regarding the reinstatement of the Jesuits. All dated Jan. 19, 1657. 2 pages (f. 367). (Box 94, Folder 56)
  - Relatione della corte di Roma fatta del 1647 in Venetia. Copy of the report from Rome by Alvise Contarini, Venetian Ambassador in Rome under Innocent X. 41 pages, numbered ff. 368-388. (Box 94, Folder 57)
  - Erizzo. Relatione della Corte di Roma fatta al...Doge et all' Senato Veneto. A detailed report on Rome to the Doge and the Senate of Venice by Erizzo, returning from his embassy in Rome. Dated Oct. 29, 1702. 77 pages, numbered ff. 389-419. (Box 94, Folder 58)
  - (Ferdinando Carlo, Duke of Mantua). Copy of a letter written in the name of the Duke of Mantua to Leopold I, recommending the Duke to the Emperor, explaining that he is not hostile at all but most loyal. Unsigned and undated (c. 1704). 11 pages, numbered ff. 420-425. (Box 94, Folder 59)
- MISCELLANY
  Seven printed and 29 manuscript pieces, in Italian, Latin, and Spanish, comprising 677 pages, numbered ff. 1-379. 4to (unless otherwise stated). Contemporary vellum (parts of spine missing). Italy, second half of the 17th century.
  - Narratione della Segnalata Vittoria ottenuta dall'Armata Olandese sopra l'Inglese, A vista del Porto di Livorno, à 13 di Marzo, 1653. The account of a victory by the Dutch at Livorno during the naval war between Holland and England. 4 leaves. Printed pamphlet. Small 4to. Numbered ff. 1-4. Livorno, 1653. (Box 95, Folder 1)
  - Ponce de Leon, Rodrigo, Count of Arcos. With woodcuts of the Madonna and Child, the Spanish Royal Arms, and an unidentified coat of arms. Printed leaflet. 2 leaves, folio (holes in upper margin, effecting some letters). Napoli, Camillo Cavallo, 1647. A proclamation by the Count of Arcos, then Viceroy of Naples, during the Masaniello rebellion in Naples. Apparently extremely rare, not in Palau nor the Hisp. Society of America. (Box 95, Folder 2)
  - Juan d'Austria. Printed broadside (some stains). Folio, folded, numbered ff. 7-8. Dated Jan. 27, 1648. Naples, G.B. Orlandi, 1648. Proclamation by John of Austria, natural son of Philip IV of Spain, during the Masaniello Rebellion. Extremely rare, not in Palau or in the Hisp. Society of America. (Box 95, Folder 3)
  - Pacelli, Paolo d'Aversa. Oratione... Printed pamphlet. 11 leaves, numbered ff. 9-19. With woodcut of Manzoli's arms on title and fine historiated woodcut initials. Holes in last leaf, with the loss of a word. Small 4to. Naples, G.B. Cappelli, 1583. A eulogistic speech on the occasion of Manzoli having been created Bishop of Aversa in 1581. Not in the catalogues of the BM or BN. (Box 95, Folder 4)
  - Prevelli, Fra. Costanzo, O.M. Risposta alla Molto Rev. Madre Suor Clara... Printed pamphlet. 4 leaves, numbered ff. 20-23. N.p., n.d. (closely cut at bottom). Dated at the end of the letter Pianasca, Dec. 1, 1647. Not in the catalogues of the BN or BM. (Box 95, Folder 5)
  - Per gli emergenti di Modono Discorso. Printed anonymous pamphlet on the opposition of Modena to Rome, advising Rome on the best position to take. Undated, around 1653. 10 leaves, numbered ff. 24-33. (Box 95, Folder 6)
  - Cesi, Cardinal Pietro Donato. Copia di lettera scritta...al Sig. Luigi d'Aro in risposta alla scrittura...publicata dal Sig. Balii di Valenze... dell'anno 1654. Copy of a letter in response to Estampes de Valençay, the French Ambassador in Rome, who had written instructions to Ambassadors. A French translation of Cardinal Cesi's letter was published in Recueil de divers relations, in 1681. For Valency's instructions, see Pastor XIV/1, p. 29, n. 2. Ms. 18 pages, numbered ff. 34-42. (Box 95, Folder 7)
  - Retz, Cardinal, Archbishop of Paris. Lettera...alli...Arcivescovi, e vescovi delle Chiese di Francia. Copy of a letter written by Cardinal Retz in Rome, where he had just arrived (Nov. 30, 1654) on his flight from France, where Mazarin had him imprisoned. He is protesting here about the violation of his rights. Dated Dec. 14, 1654. A French version of this letter was published in Paris in 1654. Ms. Title and 73 pages, numbered ff. 46-83. (Box 95, Folder 8)
  - Risposta ad' Alcuni Manifesti é Cartelli pubblicati à nome de Francesci e loro seditioni parteggiani parla sollevatione di Napoli. An answer from Rome to broadsides and pamphlets published by the French siding with the rebellion in Naples. Unsigned and undated, c. 1650. On the last page, a Latin pasquinade on the King of France. 48 pages, numbered ff. 88-112. (Box 95, Folder 9)
  - Pesaro, Giovanni, Doge of Venice. Extract from Pesaro's relation of an embassy to Pope Alexander VII. The complete relation was published in a collection of Relazioni degli Stati Europaei, Ser. III, vol. 2, in 1856. 3 pages, numbered ff. 114-115. 8vo. (Box 95, Folder 10)
  - Alexander VII, Pope. Dilectis filiis, nobilibus viris Bertuccio Valerio Duci, et remp. Venetiarum. Copy of a Latin letter of thenks by Pope Alexander VII to the Doge and the Republic of Venice, dated Rome, Jan. 27, 1657. Pastor XIV/1, p. 363, mentions the letter, the original of which is in the Papal Secret Archives. 2 pages (f. 116). 8vo. (Box 95, Folder 11)
  - Venetias...D. de Plessis Besançon Legato...apud Remp. Venetianum. Copies of three letters in Latin to the French Legate Du Plessis-Besançon in Venice, to Cardinal Mazarin, and to Louis XIV, all possibly written by a Jesuit in Rome, thanking them for the council in the Venetian senate of Jan. 19, 1657, which permitted the return of the Jesuits. All are dated Rome, Jan. 29, 1657. 2 pages (f. 117) 8vo. (Box 95, Folder 12)
  - Caracciolus, Antonius, Clericus Regularis. A Latin treatise on the history and rules of the Order of the Clerks Regulars, in answer to questions. Undated. Caracciolus published Constitutiones Clericorum Regularium in 1610. Ms. 21 pages, numbered ff. 118-128. Partly damp-stained. (Box 95, Folder 13)
  - Risposta al Manifesto dell Arciduca Leopoldo...pretende di Justicare la priggionia del Duca di Lorena. A protest against he arrest in 1654 of Charles IV, Duke of Lorraine, by Archduke Leopold William, Governor of the Netherlands. Undated and unsigned manuscript. 6 pages, numbered ff. 130-132. (Box 95, Folder 14)
  - Trattato sopra La Mossa dell'Arme Fra Urbano VIII, e li Prencipi d'Italia per Le pretentioni d'Ambe Le parti sopra Castro... A comprehensive and richly documented treatise on the War for Castro between Rome under Urban VIII and the Italian states, apparently written before peace was made in 1644. This treatise seems not to be known to Pastor (XIII/2, pp. 863-875) and was apparently never published. Title, table of contents, and 119 pages, numbered ff. 134-195. (Box 95, Folder 15)
  - Marchesi, Francesco Elio. Additiones ad Libellum F.E. Marchesii Andreas Bolutius utriusque Juris Doctor. Additions to a genealogical work by Marchesi, a Neapolitan, of which no printed edition exists. The additions by Andreas Bolutius are present in a quick draft and in a clean copy. Altogether 10 pages, numbered ff. 196-202. (Box 95, Folder 16)
  - Piscicello, Alfonso. Lettera all...Marchese d'Oriolo del conso supremo di sua Maesta Cattolica. A letter on the history of the nobility on Naples and of one of Philip IV's councillors there. 4 pages, numbered ff. 203-204. Undated and unsigned. (Box 95, Folder 17)
  - Philip IV, King of Spain. Lettera scritta... responsiva al Breve di...Alessandro settimo... transferita da Spagnolo in Italiano. Copy of a letter of Philip IV, written in response to a Breve of Pope Alexander VII. 2-1/2 pages, numbered ff. 207-208. (Box 95, Folder 18)
  - Philip IV, King of Spain. Magnificis...viris fidelibus...nostre fidelissime Civitatis Neapolis. Copy of a letter in Spanish by Philip IV to his Neapolitan subjects. Dated Madrid, March 11, 1655. 2 pages (f. 209). (Box 95, Folder 19)
  - Il 16 di Giugno 1656. Fatto consiglio il Sig. Duca di Modena... Apparently a military pact between Milan, Modena, etc., dated 1656. 3 pages, numbered ff. 211-212. (Box 95, Folder 20)
  - Testamento fatto dalle fortezza di Valenza per la Sua Caduta in mano del Serenissimo di Modena. Testament made by the Fortress of Valenza when it fell into the hands of the Duke of Modena. Dated Nov. 5, 1656. 9 pages, numbered ff. 213-217. (Box 95, Folder 21)
  - Richelieu, Jean Armand Du Plessis de, Cardinal. Vite sinopsis inscribendo Tumolo. A Latin synopsis of Cardinal Richelieu's life, to be written on his tomb. It appeared in print, without place and date, shortly after Richelieu's death in 1642. (See Cat. of the BM). 6 pages, numbered ff. 219-221. (Box 95, Folder 22)
  - (Rodolfo, Cardinal Ottavio). Fr. Nicholas Rodolfo Florentino Ottavii... Latin panegyric on the death of Cardinal Rodolfo in 1650. 2 pages (f. 222). (Box 95, Folder 23)
  - Adorni. A genealogy of the noble Genoese family Adorno. With a genealogical table, dated Bologna, 1597. 6 pages, numbered ff. 223-229. (Box 95, Folder 24)
  - Bolognino. Trattato della Famiglia Bologninos. A genealogy of this noble Italian family, with a genealogical table, dated Bologna, 1597. 6 pages, numbered ff. 231-235. (Box 95, Folder 25)
  - (Florence. Criminal Law). Copia della risposta... estrattione de pretensi sicarii di Fiorenza. Copy of a treatise on Criminal Law, dealing with the problem of ecclesiastical or worldly authorities; written in answer (?) to an edict by Ferdinand II de'Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany. Unsigned, undated. Damp stained on top, effecting the heading of the first leaf. 40 pages, numbered ff. 239-256. (Box 95, Folder 26)
  - Louis XIII, King of France. Forma della Gratia Concessa del Rè a'suoi Sudditi della Rocella. Sopra il Perdono da essi domandato à S.M. intorno alla loro Ribellione. Printed pamphlet, dated Oct. 28, 1628. 4 leaves, numbered ff. 259-262. Small 8vo. Louis XIII's pardon of the rebellion of the Huguenots in La Rochelle. Very rare. Not in the catalogues of the BN or BM. (Box 95, Folder 27)
  - (Florence. Criminal Law). Copia d'una Lettera intorno all'estrattione de i Sicarii di Fiorenza. Copy of a letter on criminals in Florence. Undated and unsigned. Answer to this letter, see no. 26 above. 18 pages, numbered ff. 263-271. (Box 95, Folder 28)
  - (Florence. Criminal law). Copia della risposta data ad una fra'intorno all'estrattione de pretensi Sicarii di Fiorenza. Copy of the answer to the previous item (no. 29); identical with no. 26, a cleaner and more legible copy. 42 pages, numbered ff. 276-296. (Box 95, Folder 29)
  - (Florence. Criminal law). Copia d'una lettera intorno all'estrattione de i Sicarii di Fiorenza. Another copy of no. 28. 15 pages, numbered ff. 297- 304. (Box 95, Folder 30)
  - Alfonso II d'Este, Duke of Ferrara. Copy of a pact between the Dukes of Mantua, Parma, and Ferrara, dated, June 27, 1593. 3 pages, numbered ff. 307-308. (Box 95, Folder 31)
  - Informatione del Regno di Polonia. A report on Poland, unsigned and undated. Possibly written by the Nuncio Caligari or by his successor Bolognetti, between 1580 and 1590. 15 pages, numbered ff. 309- 316. (Box 95, Folder 32)
  - Ruggieri, Giulio. Della relatione di Mons. Ruggieri stato Nuntio al Re di Polonia l'anno 1568. Ruggieri, Nuncio in Poland, sent this detailed report on Poland to Pope Pius V, giving an interesting account of the political, economic, and religious status of the country. See Pastor VIII, p. 502, n. 4 listing other ms. copies of this report. 48 pages, numbered ff. 317-341. (Box 95, Folder 33)
  - Viaggio di Venetia à Cracouia per Terra. An interesting list of distances between Cracow and Venice, possibly compiled by or for Ruggieri (see above item) or any other nuncio in Poland. The distances from stop to stop are given, along with alternate routes. Travel by waterways is not recommended as being too cold. 5 pages, narrow 4to, between f. 342 and 343. (Box 95, Folder 34)
  - (Odoardo Farnese, Duke of Parma). Copia della Lettera scritta dal serenissimo de Parma al Sig. Cavaliere Carandini suo Residente in Roma. Copy of a letter of instruction by the Duke of Parma to his representative in Rome, signed and dated Piacenza, Sept. 1635. 6 pages, numbered ff. 343-345. (Box 95, Folder 35)
  - Grandes de España. Detailed statistics of the government of Spain under the reign of Philip IV (1621-1665), including the royal households, government agencies, the nobility and clergy, the knights of the Order of the Golden Fleece, the army and navy, the Viceroys in Spain and Portugal, Italy, and the colonial possessions in the East and West Indies. In Spanish. 64 pages, numbered ff. 347-379. (Box 95, Folder 36)
- HISTORICAL DOCUMENTS, 12 manuscript documents in a calligraphic hand
  comprising 610 pages, numbered ff. 1-307. 4to. Contemporary vellum. Italy, 17th century.
  - Commendone, Giovanni Francesco, Bishop of Zante. Discorso sopra la Corte di Roma...poi Car.li. da Papa Pio Quarto. A 17th century ms. copy of a discourse on the state of the Papal court, written c. 1564, when Commendone returned from the Council of Trent. Pastor (VII, pp. 327-332) devotes a long appreciation to this discourse and lists all known ms. copies (pp. 661-663). The present ms. seems to be the only one to mention Pope Pius IV (1559-1565), thereby confirming Pastor's tentative date of 1564. 223 pages, numbered ff. 1-112. (Box 96, Folder 1)
  - Pace facta fra il Re Filippo et il Re Henrico del anno 1559. Account of the peace between Philip II of Spain and Henri II of France, with a copy of the Peace Treaty of Chateau-Cambrésis. 82 pages, numbered ff. 113-153. (Box 96, Folder 2)
  - Foscari, Marco. Relatione...nell'Illustrissimo et Ecclesiastissimo Consiglio dipregadi di Venetia della legatione di Firenze. A detailed account of Florence by Foscari, the Venetian legate under Pope Clement VII (1523-1534). 84 pages, numbered ff. 154-195. Wormholes in blank margin of last leaves. (Box 96, Folder 3)
  - (Bongiovanni, Bernardo, Bishop of Camerino, Nuncio in Poland). Relatione del Re di Polonia, et suoi stati. Report on Sigismund II King of Poland and the state of Poland, probably written by Bongiovanni, Papal nuncio in Poland 1560-1563. Includes copy of a Latin document. 34 pages, numbered ff. 196-212. (Box 96, Folder 4)
  - Quale Pontifex Maximus in ure Regis Eligendi deliberatione... Document in Latin, apparently concerning the election of Henri de Valois as King of Poland in 1572. 36 pages, numbered ff. 213-230. (Box 96, Folder 5)
  - Sigismund II August, King of Poland. Copies of 3 letters in Latin, written by the King of Poland to the Papal Nuncio in Poland, Bernardo Bongiovanni, dated Vilnia, March 6, 1562, Oct. 27, 1561, and Aug. 2, 1562. 9 pages, numbered ff. 231-235. (Box 96, Folder 6)
  - Catharina, Queen of Poland. Wife of Sigismund August. Copy of a letter to Bernardo Bongiovanni, Nuncio in Poland, dated Grodno, Feb. 22, 1563. In Latin. 2 pages, numbered ff. 235-236. (Box 96, Folder 7)
  - (Henri of Valois, King of Poland). Forma coronationis Serenissimi Regis Poloniae in sede Sancti Stanislai Cracoviae fatte XXI Februarii 1574. Copy of the coronation rites, in Latin, at the coronation of Henri de Valois as the King of Poland. 7 pages, numbered ff. 237-240. (Box 96, Folder 8)
  - Malatesta, Giacomo. Perche mentre Io Giacomo Malatesta ero prigione de Turchi... A report on the Turks, from a prisoner, who used the occasion of his imprisonment for observation. 32 pages, numbered ff. 241-256. (Box 96, Folder 9)
  - Esito della depositoria... A list of moneys paid to Cardinal Borromeo, Cardinal Montepulciano, and to the College of the Archives, etc., 1 page (f. 257). (Box 96, Folder 10)
  - Successo del Principe di Salerno. On the controversies concerning the new prince of Salerno, c. 1552, referring to the role of Ascanio Colonna, etc. 52 pages, numbered ff. 258-283. (Box 96, Folder 11)
  - Oratio de bello contra Venetos indicendo coram Serenissimo Maximiliano Ces. in conventu Auguste Vindeliciorum Anno Dni. MDX. Speech on the war against Venice at the Augsburg Diet of 1510, in Latin. 48 pages, numbered ff. 284-307. Apparently the last page is missing. (Box 96, Folder 12)
- POLITICAL DOCUMENTS
  Five manuscript documents (and table of contents), comprising 649 pages, numbered ff. 1-331. Some browning throughout. Large 4to. Contemporary vellum. Italy, c. 1625.
  - Cueva, Alfonso de la, Marques de Bedmar. Relatione del Governo della Serenissima Republica di Venetia, fatta dal Marchese di Bedmar, hoggi Cardinale de la Cueva. This political report on Venice was written by Alfonso de la Cueva after 1619 when he became Cardinal and before 1629, when he was named Archbishop of Oviedo. This contemporary ms. copy has the title set with a fine armorial pen drawing. Title and 341 pages, numbered ff. 1-172. Holes in blank upper margin of first 11 leaves. (Box 97, Folder 1)
  - Cueva, Alfonso de la, Marques de Bedmar. Instruttione...à D. Luigi Bravo suo successore, circa il modo còl quale si dourà governare nella sua Ambasciaria appresso le Republica di Venetia. Copy of the instructions of Cueva, Spanish Ambassador in Venice, to his successor Don Luigi Bravo. With calligraphically written title, with flourishes and floral ornaments. Undated. Title and 57 pages, numbered ff. 172-202. (Box 97, Folder 2)
  - In L. Banck's Bizzarrie politiche, 1658, an Instruzzione secreta data...à Luis Brava is published, which might be the same or similar to the present text. See Brit. Mus. Cat., under "Cueva."
  - Cueva, Alfonso de la, Marquis de Bedmar. Relatione di Venetia fatta da D. Alfonso de la Cueva...già Ambasciadore per la Maestà Catholica presso detta Republica hoggi Cardinale di Santa Chiesa. Calligraphically written contemporary copy of a report on Venice by Cueva, who had been sent to Venice as an Ambassador of King Philip III of Spain. (Box 97, Folder 3)
  - The report was probably done between 1619 (when Cueva became cardinal) and 1621 (when Philip III died). It contains a detailed account of the geography of Venice and its environs, its government, people, customs, and diplomatic relations. 75 pages, numbered ff. 203-240.